why you will it last exactly why do they
always go hand in hand why when there is
lust there will be ill will
well then that's a dependency on lust
which is always directed towards things
in the world that that comes the
possibility that other people might get
in your way yep but not even more
acutely from your point of view
so the dependency on lust how's that
maintained how do you perpetuate your
own dependency on lust
by being also
yeah but how are you being lustful yeah
danger in being lost for by not knowing
the escape from that
yeah so person doesn't know the Escape
yes but can find this key
by not doing certain things which if
you're doing you're keeping your
dependence on lust yes so what are those
things that you should talk about that
you shouldn't do while you're still
dependent on lust
oh what you should not do is I tend to
things that are provocative lost exactly
so okay virtual Center strength but then
you should not be grasping the features
of beautiful that are increasing the
last uh increasing the wanting increasing the
uh increasing the wanting increasing the
sensuality and it's because
if you unchecked are constantly grasping
the features of beautiful let your mind
well on them warn them Delight in them
welcome them you will be unable to help
yourself but grasp the features of ugly
when you experience the disagreeable
experience in other words you will be
grasping the features of hate
when the experience changes so if you
meet somebody who is not a lovely person
and who is quite unpleasant your mind
will not be able to not pick the
features of resistance to that and anger
and everything else that will come out
of it because it's operating on the
level of science because the mind
operates on picking up the features yeah
that's it it has not discerned a bigger
picture and learn how not to pick the
features and signs and features of
beautiful so there will be signs and
features of beautiful waiting but you
don't need to pick them up but you can't
not pick them up because all you know is
acting to a centrality
same there will be features of ugly and
unpleasant but you can't not pick them up and get
but you can't not pick them up and get
all wound up and angry
because you keep acting towards and
subjects but you're not angry
but you're not angry
so you can Withrow if I cannot get angry
now well
you can achieve that by not being
Central either when you're not angry
if you haven't uh understood it
correctly you will still be blaming that
on the situation not being well that's
what it means that's what sensuality
means that's what their will means means
seeing past where the problem actually
is and assuming it on the sense objects
so
the last the delighted gratification is
not in the sense objects it's in your
happiness and Delight on account of it
but you you see way way past that
immediately you're down into the objects
equally when it's unpleasant
the the pain the discomfort of it it's
not because of some hateful word you're
experiencing and so on it's because your
mind's resisting it but you you don't
see that level you're way past it onto
the face of the person that's annoying
it
so through cultivating sensuality not
practicing sense restraint you are
cultivating your mind of overlooking
where the problem is not seeing that
that domain that is that is all that
there is to it but in order to see that
level in order to be able to recognize
it endure it sufficiently until you see
your intentions in regard to it you've
had to have out of Faith or some sort of
pondering and understanding withdrawn
yourself from acting out towards sense
objects beautiful or ugly so precepts
acting towards sensuality acting out of
anger real will hatred bad speech all of
that needs to have been honed in and
restrained
so in other words it's impossible to not
to be able to not grasp the signs and
features and Overlook where the problem
is in regard to centrality real well
if you still not withdrawn from it with
your body if you're still acting out and
seeking
thing is called things that entail
suffering to kadama
the dumbest
let's go like a few questions
which we can stop it
says when a biku completely understands
the comings and goings as I translated
that that
origin and cessation
we completely understands the comings
and goings of things that entail
suffering then Central Pleasures have been seen by
then Central Pleasures have been seen by
him in such a way that as he looks at
them Central desire does not lie blatant
Central desire does not lie blatant
within him
then he has comprehended a way of living
whereby evil and wholesome states of
greed lust and sadness or displeasure did not
lust and sadness or displeasure did not
flow in upon him so
so
that's that that's the first statement
and it's just broken up into
a few parts uh the first
question is and how does a biku
completely understand the comings and
goings of things that entail suffering
how is that understood any ideas
um it's not a trick question yeah I know
but I'm wondering
and falling
yeah just how it and the translation is
like how it's produced and how it's how
it's kind of falls apart
kind of falls apart
I do
know
how do you understand that I allowing
I allowing
than to enjoy
um to
without um um
interfering
or acting out of the
there's one yeah and I would say it
doesn't really say it there but it does
say such is form yeah I was
what are the things that entail
suffering so good this is for this is
its origin this is his cessation so to
me they're saying
and how does he understand things well
he
investigates it
the problem there is though that
can investigate and
get the right answers but still on the
abstract level
oh yeah subject is formed I mean the
whole commentarial texts were written on
what the form is or It's Made Up
made up of that okay I got information
thus this is the form but no it starts
with endurance
by not acting out of the form that
pressures you
not acting out of the concern in regard
to your form that you're pressured by
by Discerning the nature of it enduring
there on its own you're paired with it
then you get to see such is the form
like you might not know the information
how the form came about and you don't
need to you can still understand the
aggregate or form but having it endures
you know such is formed and then you
start to let it evil you let it into it
then you get to see all this other but
that needs to be qualified because as I
said people already think they can
practice the Dharma without a right view
means they can think that all this
information you get and you learn about
the first second fourth John or the five
upgrades all of that applies to them
already but it doesn't
in order for it to apply you need to
create a basis for basis for which to
apply and that's the basis precepts
guarding of the sense doors the Mind
purification development on account of
it and then yeah such is the form that
endures because see even people they would then
because see even people they would then
be finding out what is the form where it
comes from uh why is it here how is it
here what created it what will be its
hand all of these questions
would be rooted in trying to get rid of
the form so they don't understand what
form is because they don't want to
endure it because it's unpleasant the
pressure is uncomfortable so I'm
practicing the Dharma just to get rid of
it
so the understanding Begins by not
acting out on that level
and then you will know what form is form
is there and that it says in other
suitors he doesn't care whether it's far
or near personal impersonal up down left
right past future he knows the aggregate
to form as aggregate to form it's there
that's all I need to know within that
then you can actually understand oh yeah
that's how form is that's how it
increases that's how it decreases the
entire extent of it has been abandoned
by me because I'm not acting out of it
anymore I'm not trying to get rid of it
I'm not taking the pleasure through it
and then same goes for the feeling
perception intentions and consciousness right
so you can get all that information yeah
but then
the results should be that
when Central pleasures
when the essential Pleasures available
he should have no desire yeah there
blatant infatuation for it because he's
understood the form is understood the feeling so
the form is understood the feeling so
so you've got all this information vast
amount of
but they're still there so yeah that
should be an indication that you you
just have information that's
that doesn't apply to you you're not
applying it you're not seeing it right
you can't understand it without seeing
without seeing the escape from it
basically or without uh having the
passion in regard to his
diminished or not so not be able to at
the same reasons at the same time
they're incompatible yeah by seeing the
gratification danger escape
and how our essential Pleasures seen by
him in such a way that as he looks at
them Central desire does not lie latent
Central desire does not lie latent
within him
so how will Central Pleasures seen yes
impermanent
that's why they are unsatisfying they
don't last
so he sees them as
unsatisfied as unsatisfying impermanent
unsatisfaction but also
ugly yeah you've got to be seeing them
as actually not attractive
but as I said before many times
you won't see that if your only concern
is to act out towards more pleasure or
get rid of the pain of not acting out
those pleasure
I must place this with the Suba Suba
Suba because it Suba bothers me too much
while you're looking at Suba as the
Sutra says why are you looking at the
beautiful while he sees it
he is not attracted to it anymore
there is no underlying desire and luster
it can overwhelm the Mind why because
while he sees it he sees the ugly within
it because that's what truly is if you
weren't so freedom from sensuality will
not be possible nor sensuality would be
a problem
but usually the problem because it's a
contradiction it's a bait it's a trap
that's not understood it's not
understood for what it really is
and why it's not understood for what it
really is because the mind
is so used to and has been doing it for
so long just picks the Beautiful
like imagine you have a ball
of just food and rubbish and dirt
everything just mixed in it
with some pieces that actually taste
nice but it's all part of the same mix well
but it's all part of the same mix well
that's sensuality just focusing on the
bits that taste nice and ignoring where
it comes from and what it remains while
you're eating it
so you have to stop ignoring it while it
is there
and that's why I keep saying you can't
just yes you have to be restrained and
not just carelessly engage with auto
sensuality but at the same time you have
to recognize that those thoughts are
really such pressures are really such
attraction is really such and you have
to stop acting out of it and one way of
acting out of it is trying to replace it
with a silver or whatever else no you
need to understand it
so you will not see what lies at the
other end of Suba if you're too
preoccupied in trying to get rid of it
try directing out towards it
and get you know free from that pressure
that imposes over you
or distracting yourself with other
thoughts just so that until this
disappears because you can't deal with
it
precepts are there to protect you
so you don't actually if you can't deal
with it mentally so you don't act out
okay endure the pressure of the pole so
that next time you see something that
used to pull you there will be no
underlying tendency on the like
basically waiting to pounce on you
because you actually saw it as ugly as I
wanted you saw it as burning embers
you saw it as burning embers
yeah that's it so yeah he's
Essentials how essential Pleasures
seemed by him in such a way that as he
looks at them
not tries to get rid of them or run away
from them
concentrate concentrate concentrate
super super why because you don't want
to deal with the pain because there's no
problem you haven't acted out
you're obviously not wanting it mentally
so you're not delighting in it so what's
the problem then why can't you bear that
pain oh because you don't want pain
oh because you don't want pain
which means by proxy you still want
pledge that's not this anymore sure
so for as long as you tried as we said
before as long as you're trying to get
rid of the pain then replace you with
pleasure you will want to have pleasure and not
you will want to have pleasure and not
have pain thus you're still very much
within Central domain on account of you
trying to overcome your sensuality
so don't act out don't Delight in it but
then when seen when thought of see
through it
not at the expense of it
yeah see and as this this simile says
see the the danger in it you know
suppose so how does he see look at
sensual Pleasures or beauty
Suppose there is a charcoal bit deeper
than a man's height filled with Glenn
coals a man would come along wanting to
live not wanting to die
Desiring happiness and averse to
suffering then two strong men would grab
him by both arms and drag him towards
that charcoal pit the man would wriggle
his body this way and that for what
reason because he knows I will fall into
this charcoal pit and I will thereby
death or deadly suffix so it is
dangerous this thing that's beautiful well
this thing that's beautiful well
ironically enough
when people try to get rid
of these Central perceptions
they're trying to get rid of the pain of
recognizing the charcoal pit in them
that's what they're trying to get rid of
concentrate don't think about don't
think about remove the thoughts remove
the thoughts remove the thoughts it's
basically just stop showing me the pain
of the charcoal pit because I can't bear
it why because it's still bad this seems
painful and
go in this direction that is dangerous
leave that pain of the pressure donate
thou by Body by speech don't mentally
prolifer it further but then thoughts
that are there that are pressuring you
painful that's what you train in regard
to and then you realize well yeah this
pain I'm just habitually trying to sort
of evade no
that is the pain of these things
and I'm not there now
because I already been withdrawn by not
acting towards now I just needed to stop
resisting that pain to see where that
pain truly belongs
it's not to me it's not because of my
sense restraint it's not because of mine
it's because that's what sensuality is a
charcoal pit
and then you won't have to be
restraining yourself anymore because you
wouldn't want to go into a charcoal pit
so seeing a danger
and then how from that point how has a
big who comprehended a way of living
whereby evil and wholesome states of
greed and sadness or
do not flow in upon him how
how
what would be the way of living
that he has discovered now
that will keep him safe
and making cross to the other Shore
I know beautiful path yeah
what else yeah well and but what you
said in the games is uh Wellness yeah
yeah
so this is to how I should live now okay
for my own welfare which is what I
always wanted
that's why I was seeking sensuality and
safety and comfort and you know identity
in the world is because I thought that
was for my own welfare I thought it was
for my well-being
now I recognize no that was all a trap
yeah I still want the well-being of myself
I still want the well-being of myself
that's still a valid thing but now you
recognize it with that welfare truly is
it still remains you see the criteria
remains but now you go very differently
about it
and the simile suppose a man would enter
a thorny Forest there would be thorns in
front of him Thorns behind Thorns to the
left Thorns the right Thorns below him
the Thorns above him he would go forward
mindfully he would go back mindfully
thinking May no Thorn stab me so too
whatever in the world has a pleasing and
agreeable nature is called a thorn in
the noble ones discipline so don't stab
it so I want it yeah and just there is
stones be careful
and then having understood this way of
living
once you then
make understand uh restraint and
non-restraints yeah you should know the difference like
yeah you should know the difference like
okay so now how do I be careful
you understand the extent
of restraint
and what it leads to and the extent of
non-restraint and what it leads to not
just the immediate artist friend I don't
restrain that is life a mode of being of
restraint leads away from this
leads away from this
and he understands it he's not just
taking it on faith to practice any
strength he sees a direct result of
restraint
and direct result of non-restraint
simultaneously there he sees it
and it's not even a matter of Choice by
that point what he will choose and do
and uh so what does he understand
there's non-restraints here having
I've just translated different here
having perceived an object with the
senses a bigger is intent Upon A
pleasing form and repelled by this
pleasing form
he lives without having set up
recollection of the body with a limited
narrow mind
and in that way he does not know a
liberated mind or a Liberation through
wisdom whereby those evil and awesome
States completely cease
and the opposite is true
uh he understands the restraints having
perceived an object with the senses
because not intent upon the pleasing
form and not repelled by the displeasing
so he understands what the restraint is
restraint is not being intent upon
restraint does not mean not having eyes
and not seeing things
strength means understanding the
restraint or non-restrained means
understanding where the problem of lust
and non-lust
where the problem will last is
and it's in grasping the beautiful signs
not getting rid of the beautiful things
in the world
if this leads to increase of loss say
five keep attending to these signs they
remain present
but I choose to then attend to them
further mind of lust will increase and he fully
mind of lust will increase and he fully
understands that the animal will go
Wilder I attend it it almost listens to
me now I'm letting it go wild again
if I don't attend to these things then I
still present there I'm not trying to
get rid of them either but I simply
don't attend to them
the animal will remain calm and the mind
will turn to a Liberation not towards
lost and his delicacy and understood
but then so he lives in such a way
he's restrained
but then occasionally due to a lapse of
memory mindfulness evil and wholesome
intentions connected with the
defilements arise in him
slow might be the arising obvious
recollection and he's remembering but
then he quickly abandons the Spells and
puts an end to them so
even though it it does arise again you
know he has been so see
he puts he he dispels he gets rid of
them he puts an end to them how
by slowly
slow arising of the context of the
mindfulness of what is Peril what is
danger what is sensory strength not by
he gets rid of them he gets rid of them
by thinking about something else no he
gets rid of them but but
recreating recollecting the bigger picture then he
recollecting the bigger picture then he
has discerned beforehand that's exactly
basically as the other symbol in the
suit that says like you heat up a pan
and as the drops of water fall they will
evaporate immediately the pan is hot
so he gets rid of them by heating the
pan not by catching the drops of water
and preventing it from falling onto the
pan no keep the pan hot nothing can
stick to it
no water can can soak it
well that's that's the semination
just as a man the two or three drops of
water fall onto an iron plate heated for
a whole day
might be the falling off the drops of
water but then they would quickly
vaporize and vanish
and uh it's almost
that's a big who has
biku has comprehended a way of living
whereby evil and wholesome states of
greed and sadness do not float in upon
him
and when he is living in such a way
various other people might invite him to
accept wealth
there might be some options available
some praise gain Fame come good man why
let these robes weigh you down
[Laughter] why roam about with a shaven head and a
why roam about with a shaven head and a
begging bull
come having returned to that lower life
enjoy wealth and do notorious Deeds
indeed when a beaker is living in that
way it is impossible that he will give
up the training and return to the lower
life and a set of the simile
and a set of the simile
suppose that when the river Ganges
Slants and slopes and inclines towards
the east and a great crowd of people
would come along bring bringing a shovel
and a basket thinking we will make this
River Ganges slant and slope and climb
towards the West
what do you think because would that
great crowd of people be able to make
the river Ganges slant slope and he
climb towards the West
no available set for what reason because
the river Ganges slant slopes and it
climbs towards the east and is not easy
to make its slides and inclined towards
the West
that crowd great crowd of people would
only reap fatigue and disappointment
likewise it is with the biker whose mind
has for a long time slanted sloped and
inclined towards Detachment seclusion
thus it is impossible that he will give
up the training in return to the low
life so it's completely protected really
no matter how many people or pressures
are external possibility invitations
they'll just fall flat anyways